<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A copie of the articles and conditions of his excellencie, granted to the gouernour, captaines, officers and souldiers of the garrison of the towne of Graue Also a copie of a letter dated the 28. of September 1602. in the Hage, sent from a man of worship to his friends here in England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12196</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118549</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853756</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853756</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19151</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02049)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19151)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1205:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A copie of the articles and conditions of his excellencie, granted to the gouernour, captaines, officers and souldiers of the garrison of the towne of Graue Also a copie of a letter dated the 28. of September 1602. in the Hage, sent from a man of worship to his friends here in England.</title>
                  <author>Maurice, Prince of Orange, 1567-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by F. Kingston] for Matthew Law,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19151:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19151:1"/>
            <p>A COPIE OF THE ARTICLES AND CONDITIONS OF his Excellencie, granted to the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Captaines, Officers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of the Garriſon of the towne of <hi>Graue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo a copie of a Letter dated the</hi> 28. <hi>of</hi> September 1602. in the <hi>Hage,</hi> ſent from a man of Worſhip to his friends here in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed for <hi>Matthew Law,</hi> 1602.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19151:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19151:2"/>
            <head>A Letter written from the <hi>Haghe the</hi> 11. <hi>day of September</hi> 1602. Stilo Anglio.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Came yeſterday from <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negem,</hi> two leagues from the towne of <hi>Graue.</hi> On VVedneſday wee heard they of the <hi>Graue</hi> ſent out to parley, when the Mines were ready to be blowne vnder their wals, and that night the next morning fell to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, to retire towards <hi>Dieſt</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricht</hi> with 140. wagons for their hurt men, with bagge and baggage. Some thinke they are much ſpent. This day they are to depart: but three hundred of our men were put in the poſſeſſion of the Caſtle, and oſtages gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. From our ſide the <hi>Ringraue</hi> is one. That day we thought it a happie parley, for the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19151:3"/>Riuer <hi>Moſa</hi> did grow, that our workes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to come vnder water, and there was feared ſome extraornarie floud of vpper water for raines. But ſince it is fallen.</p>
            <p>The towne was very ſtrong, but brought to extremitie, and well defended, of the which I will write more with the next.</p>
            <p>The Eſtates were in the Camp and viewed all the trenches, and haue reſolued to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the Germanes yet for two moneths in wages. And it is thought ſome more ſeruice is in hand, either vpon <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enlo,</hi> or to ſeeke to fight with the <hi>Admirant,</hi> being weake as it is thought, or ſome other ſeruice. The <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinados</hi> bee ſtrong, and grow daily about <hi>Hoochstrate,</hi> and ranſome all. It is thought theſe ſouldiers of <hi>Graue</hi> will doe the like if they be not payd.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19151:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE CONDITIONS, which his Excellency agreed with the</hi> Gouernour, Captaines, Officers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of the Garriſon of the towne of <hi>Graue.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>NPRIMIS, that the ſaid Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, Captaines, Officers and Souldiers, as well horſe as foote, ſhall depart the ſaid Towne, with their Horſes, Armes, furniture and baggage, their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours diſplaied, Drumme ſounding, Match alight, and their bullets in their bags.</p>
            <p n="2">2 To the end they may the better carry their baggage, their ſicke and hurt, his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie ſhall cauſe them to haue 150. wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, from hence to the towne of <hi>Dieſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 That they ſhall leaue here two Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines in hoſtage, for the aſſurance of the ſaid Chariots, horſes and driuers, till their returne.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19151:4"/>
            <p n="4">4 That his Excellencie ſhall giue them Paſport to paſſe to the towne of <hi>Dieſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 That the ſouldiers, which haue ſerued the ſaid State, ſhall enioy the ſame condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are enioyed by the ſouldiers of the ſaid Garriſon.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That all priſoners, of what qualitie or condition ſoeuer, as well of the one ſide as of the other, ſhall be at libertie, paying their charges.</p>
            <p n="7">7 That all the officers of the King, aſwell priuate as publike, of the wars or the State, ſhal depart freely with their baggage, as the Garriſon: and thoſe that cannot followe the troupes, are permitted to ſtay yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine dayes within the towne, and at their departure they ſhall haue Barques to carrie them to <hi>Mastrich;</hi> prouided that they gaue aſſurance and pledges for the ſaid Barques.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That the officers of the victuals, or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition for warre and artillerie, ſhalbe bound to deliuer the ſaid victuals, munition and artillerie, into the hands of the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that ſhall be ſent on this ſide to receiue them, without diminiſhing or waſting any
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19151:4"/>part thereof, vpon paine of forfaiting theſe conditions.</p>
            <p n="9">9 That the Gouernour, Captaines and officers doe promiſe ſo to deale with their friends, that whatſoeuer the Magiſtrate and Burgioſſes of the towne haue lent them, ſhall be repayed with all conuenient ſpeed.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That the ſaid Gouenour, Captaines and Souldiers, ſhall depart to morrow: and if perhaps they doe not depart to morrow, the ſaid Gouernour ſhall ſuffer to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Caſtle and the Bulwarke behind the Caſtle to the number of 100. men, which his Excellencie ſhall ſend to that purpoſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written at the Campe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Graue,</hi> 
                  <date>the 19. of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember. 1602.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Written be me <hi>Paulus Demetrius.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19151:5"/>
            <head>ANOTHER LETTER written out of the <hi>Hage</hi> the 28. <hi>of September.</hi> 1602.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orſhipful Sir, ſithence the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendring of the Towne of <hi>Graue,</hi> we heare his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> is inſtaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at <hi>Graue</hi> as Earle of the Countrie of <hi>Cuyck.</hi> The Dutch horſemen are licenſed to depart, and are paid for eight daies more then they haue ſerued. What we ſhall heare moreouer the time will learne. The Campe is not as yet broke vp, but the horſemen are gone by the mutined ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers towards <hi>Breda</hi> and <hi>Hoochstrate.</hi> It is ſaid they are agreed not to hurt or endo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage the vnited Countries, and prouide and ſupply their want and neceſſity for their money at <hi>Breda</hi> and there abouts. And in caſe they ſhould be aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aulted by the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19151:5"/>they may betake themſelues vnder <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenberghen</hi> and proffer ſeruice, if men would truſt them. It is reported they 1300. horſe, and ſeuen or eight hundred foote, all old ſouldiers, of al nations, none other they will accept in their companie, then thoſe which are eight moneths pay behind hand. With the remayning new-come Italians and Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, and with a companie of Boores of Wals Brabant doth the Archduke purpoſe to aſſault them: but doth not truſt his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon but by ſouldiers which are paid. What hereof ſhall enſue the time will learne. The States generall are all yet in the Campe with his Excellency, which maketh that wee doe not yet know what reſolution will be taken.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
